汝弃绝撒旦吗？
Abrenuntias satanae?
吾弃绝
Abrenuntio.
吾兹为汝施洗 奉圣父
Ego te baptizo, in nomine Patris…
圣子 圣灵之名
et Filii, et Spiritus Sancti.
一路平安 愿主与你同在
Vade in pace, et Dominus vobiscum.
阿门
Amen.
无限恩慈的主
God, of infinite goodness,
请赐美满恒久的生活
send prosperous life and long.
予无比尊贵的英格兰公主
to the high and mighty Princess of England,
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth!
不许有人质疑生育非法与否
There can be no question of illegitimacy.
你立即起草一份法案呈交国会
You will prepare a bill to put before Parliament.
规定王位第一顺位继承权
It will state that the line of succession.
确属我们的子嗣
is now firmly vested in our children…
而非他人
and no others.
谨遵陛下谕令
I shall do as Your Majesty commands.
克伦威尔先生 我心知肚明 依然有些人
I am mindful, Mr. Cromwell, that there are some people.
有些榆木脑袋
some wrong headed,
有些存有偏见的人 不会愿意
some biased people who are still unwilling.
接受我与王后婚姻的有效合法
to accept the validity of my marriage to the Queen.
鉴于此
In view of that,
我想制定些约束法案
I think some sanction should be made against them.
以让人人都有机会
Everyone will be given their opportunity.
来表现他们的忠诚
to demonstrate their loyalty.
勒德洛城堡 威尔士边界
Ludlow castle, The Welsh Marches.
我听说那女士因生了个女儿沮丧不已
I am told that the Lady is much dismayed at having given birth.
而非以前信誓旦旦的儿子
to a daughter and not the son she promised.
以我之见 这是主抛弃她的确凿证明
To my mind, it is sure proof that God has abandoned her.
我母亲 王后 近来如何？
How is my mother, the Queen?
哎呀 我没法去看她 或与她讲话
Alas, I cannot visit or speak to her.
我跟她的侍女聊过几句
I have little communications with her ladies,
她们告诉我她依然坚强
and they tell me she is still strong…
但一直在恳求国王 你的父亲
but always begs the King, your father, of his mercy,
希望他出于怜悯 允许她与你会面
to be allowed to see you.
我确信陛下有朝一日总会回心转意的
I am sure His Majesty will one day relent,
我想
for I think…
我全然相信他仍然爱我 关心我
I believe with all my heart that he still loves and cares for me.
我深有同感
I am sure that he does.
滕斯托尔主教
Bishop Tunstall.
托马斯爵士
Sir Thomas.
谢谢
Thank you.
如何有幸使尊驾光临？
To what do I owe this honour?
我们相识久矣 托马斯爵士
We have known each other a long time, Sir Thomas.
如今您退隐 无从谋面
But now you have retired from public life and I never see you.
我自然该前来问安
Naturally I was concerned about your welfare.
我过的不错 多谢关心
I am very well, thank you.
不过
But I am…
我焦虑的是我们的另一位老相识
I am exorcised by the fact that one of our old acquaintances.
- 却一直被软禁家中 - 你指费施尔主教？
- is still under house arrest. - You mean Bishop Fisher?
是的 结局让人很遗憾
Yes, the outcome is regrettable.
什么样的「结局」？
The "outcome" of what?
他不妥协的「结局」
His intransigence.
明白了
I see.
开门见山吧
Tell me,
是国王派您登门拜访的吧？
has the King sent you here to see me?
陛下希望了解
His Majesty wondered.
为何您未应邀
why you did not attend the Queen's Coronation,
参加王后加冕典礼
as you were invited to do.
关于此事 让我…
Well, in answer to that, let me…
让我对你粗表愚见
let me show my poor mind to you.
有个关于提庇留大帝的故事
There's a story about the Emperor Tiberius.
他颁布一项法律 规定某种犯罪
He had enacted a law which exacted death.
可判处死刑 除非犯罪者是处女
for a certain crime… unless the offender was a virgin.
可最终当一个处女被如此指控时
Now, when a virgin eventually appeared on the charge,
皇帝却不知该如何下手
the Emperor didn't know exactly how to proceed,
因此他的一名议员提出个绝佳的解决方案
so one of his council proposed the perfect solution:
先辣手摧花使她失贞
Let her first be deflowered,
因而她就可被依律处死
so she then can be… devoured.
有些人
There are some…
不 我就不指名道姓
and no, I won't name them.
他们先引诱你去加冕礼
who first procure you for the coronation,
然后就大肆渲染 甚至白纸黑字立此存照
next to preach at it, and then to write books defending it.
从而先玷污你
Thus they deflower you,
然后就可轻而易举地置你于死地
and will not fail soon afterwards to devour you.
但是他们永远也别妄想玷污我
But they shall never deflower me.
太动听了
That was beautiful.
您也热衷此道？
Do you play?
一向如此
All the time.
- 陛下 - 埃莉诺女士
- Majesty. - Lady Eleanor.
没关系
Never mind.
要像这样 看着
More like this. Watch.
手指像这样
Fingers like so.
不要捏箭太紧
Don't squeeze the arrow.
拉弓
Draw…
然后放箭
and release.
- 我永远办不到 - 不 你会的
- I'll never do that. - Yes, you will.
- 大臣阁下 - 公爵大人
- Mr. Secretary. - Your Grace.
- 你的儿子？- 是啊
- And your son? - Yes.
趁还没太老以前 教他些运动
I'm teaching him to sport before I get too old for it.
- 你射箭吗 克伦威尔？- 有时候 大人
- Do you shoot, Cromwell? - Sometimes, Your Grace.
大人
My Lord.
走走吧
Shall we walk?
国王有何吩咐？
What does the King want?
陛下希望你和你的妻子回宫
His Majesty would like to see you back at court. With your wife.
- 他想念大人你陪伴左右了 - 还有呢？
- He misses Your Grace's company. - And?
陛下知道您是亲皇派
His Majesty is aware that you favour the Imperialist cause.
您在议会上直言不讳
you say so openly in Council.
- 另外你也许极为同情亲王太妃？- 你不是吗？
- and have, perhaps, a great sympathy for the Dowager Princess? - Don't you?
说实话 我也是
Actually, I do.
我不是没心没肺
I'm not heartless,
不管有些人怎么想
whatever some people think.
恰恰相反
Quite the contrary.
但是我效忠国王
But I serve the King.
陛下意欲将王位继承权授予
His Majesty intends to vest the succession.
他与安妮王后的子嗣
with the children he will have with Queen Anne.
有关法案会呈交国会
A bill will go before Parliament.
他想了解您是否支持他
He wants to know if he'll have your support.
饿了？
Shh… Hungry?
- 你在做什么？- 陛下
- What are you doing? - Majesty.
难道我不可以给她喂奶吗？
May I not feed her from my own breast?
王后不做此事
Tsk, tsk. Queens don't do that…
特别是不会给女儿
especially not for a daughter.
把她交给奶妈吧
Give her back to her wet-nurse.
公主将在哈菲尔德拥有自己的领地
The Princess will shortly be given her own establishment at Hatfield.
玛丽女士也同别人一起前去听候差遣
Among others, the Lady Mary will attend and wait on her.
你指凯瑟琳的女儿？
Katherine's daughter?
是的
Yes.
让她明白一下自己的新位置也好
It is well that she knows her new place.
克伦威尔大臣在安排一切
Secretary Cromwell is arranging it.
我会给你生个儿子的
I will still give you a son.
快来吧 亲爱的
Come soon, my darling,
到我热情的床上来
to my hot bed.
女士们
Ladies.
陛下
Majesty.
爱丽丝 孩子们
Alice, children…
我亲爱的家人 我有事要宣布
My dear family, I have something to say to you.
我的收入现在
My income is now.
大不如前了
so greatly reduced, that…
我们不能再按以前的生活标准生活了
that we can no longer go on living as we are accustomed.
我的国王补助金已被取消
I am no longer the recipient of the King's bounty.
所以
And so,
生活必须从俭
I must live frugally.
缩减家用开销
and reduce my household.
可以自食其力的
Those of you who can must live in your own houses.
另立门户
and eat at your own tables.
- 但是 父亲 - 就此决定
- But, Father… - No. Come on.
凡事总是会有变化
Things inevitably must change.
你们不能永远被供养
You can't all be supported forever.
生活并非如此
Life is not like that.
现实的生活是残酷
Real life is raw.
而艰难的
and difficult.
你们必须面对现实
And you must face up to that fact.
否则就会更糟
If not to even worse things.
行了 我们吃饭吧
Come on. Let us eat.
哈福德郡 哈菲尔德宅
Hatfield House Hertfordshire.
布赖恩夫人 玛莉小姐到
The Lady Mary, Lady Bryan.
玛莉小姐
Lady Mary.
欢迎来到哈菲尔德 你的新家
Welcome to Hatfield, your new home.
我是公主的家庭教师 玛格丽特·布赖恩夫人
I am Lady Margaret Bryan, the Princess's Governess.
其他侍女都在此照顾公主
These other Ladies are also here to attend the Princess,
你也一样
as of course are you.
玛莉小姐 请允许我向你介绍
Lady Mary, may I present you to her Highness.
伊丽莎白公主殿下
the Princess Elizabeth.
有人会带你去自己的房间
You will be shown to your room.
早间祷告之后 你就可以开始工作了
You will begin your duties in the mornings, after prayers.
我要单独祷告
I shall say my prayers alone.
这是你的房间 小姐
This is your room, my Lady.
为了圣诞
Christmas.
为什么人越老 越觉得每天都是圣诞节
Why is it that as you get older, it always seems to be Christmas?
当然 对你永远是圣诞节 不是吗 勋爵
Of course, it is always Christmas for you, isn't it, my Lord?
您原本男爵而又获封一些新头衔 请指教一下？
A Baron in your own right now, and some new titles. Remind me.
御犬总监 南方五港总督
Master of Buckhounds. Lord Warden of the Cinque Ports.
对了 是不是还有一个
Ah. Was there not another one?
为疯子开的伯利恒精神病院院长？
Master of the Bedlam Hospital for the insane?
的确
Yes.
打算去看看吗
Do you plan to visit it?
我不是说作为病人进去
I don't mean as an inmate.
我拜读过你关于宫廷生活的讽刺诗
I read one of your satires about life here at court.
如果我是你 我会谨慎行事
If I were you, I'd be more careful.
那些你所取笑的人完全有能力伤害你
about poking fun at those who have the power to hurt you.
只是些友善的建议
That's just friendly advice.
过来 亲爱的
Here, my love.
我有一件礼物送给你
I have a gift for you.
太妙了 是谁的杰作
It's fantastic! Who made this?
荷尔拜因大师
Master Holbein.
此人很有天赋
The man's a genius.
你也是 我美丽的王后
As are you, my beautiful Queen.
圣诞愉快
Happy Christmas.
我还可以下手
I could still do it.
我可以找机会下毒
I could find a way to poison her.
- 不 - 但是我想
- No. - But I thought that was.
这会连累我的主人
It would be blamed on my master.
目前并不需要动手
At the moment, he doesn't need that.
他还要处理与土耳其的对战事宜
He has a war with the Turks to contend with.
- 但为什么要让世人皆知 - 别傻了 布里列顿
- But why should anyone ever know? - Don't be stupid, Brereton.
他们会查出你 然后折磨你
They would find you and torture you,
- 你会供出一切的 - 不 我不会的
- and you would tell them everything. - No, I wouldn't.
我会壮烈殉教
I'd die a martyr's death.
你不像是能经受得了折磨的人
You've never seen a man being tortured.
你现在明白了吗
Now do you understand?
切勿单独行事
You don't act alone.
查尔斯
Charles.
- 圣诞节愉快 - 陛下同乐
- Happy Christmas. - And to Your Majesty.
- 我有件礼物呈献给您 - 在哪里
- I have a gift for you. - Where is it?
得等到新一轮的国会会议 是臣的支持票
You'll have to wait until the new session of Parliament-for it's my vote.
我有何必曾对你所怀疑呢？
How could I have ever doubted you?
埃莉诺·鲁克 注意到国王看她的眼神了吗
Eleanor Luke. You see the way the King looks at her?
她是国王的情妇
She's his mistress.
除掉她
Get rid of her.
- 玛莉 - 陛下
- Mary. - Majesty.
我们得给你物色名新夫婿
We must find you a new husband.
- 我还有一件礼物奉上 - 是什么
- I have another gift for you. - Hmm?
我又有身孕了
I am with child again.
陛下 议员们
Majesty, Councillors.
这是新的继承法案
here is the new Act, the Act of Succession,
我奉命即刻传达给国会
which I am commanded to present shortly to the Houses of Parliament.
法案提名陛下与安妮王后所生
The Act nominates the children born.
子女为第一顺位继承人
of His Majesty and Queen Anne as first rightful heirs.
此法案在于保护本国
By so doing, it protects this nation.
重蹈四分五裂的复辙
from the great divisions it has suffered in the past,
诸侯觊觎宝座已久
when several different titles have pretended to the throne.
法案谨此作为警示
The Act warns that anyone saying or writing.
若有损害或诽谤
anything to the prejudice or slander.
吾王与其至亲至爱的安妮王后的
of the lawful matrimony between the King.
合法婚姻及后嗣
and his most dear and entirely beloved wife Queen Anne,
之行为
or against his heirs,
将以叛国罪论处
would be guilty of high treason,
处以极刑
for which the penalty is death.
其财产收归王室所有
and forfeiture of goods to the Crown.
「新法案要求所有臣民
"The new Act requires all the King's subjects,
进行宣誓
"if so commanded, to swear an oath.
他们将忠实 坚定 不懈 确实地
"that they shall truly, firmly, constantly, without fraud and guile,
遵守 履行 维护 保护 维持
"observe, fulfil, maintain, defend and keep.
法令的全部内容和效力「
the whole contents and effect of the Bill."
此项宣誓同样需要承认国王
This oath will also require recognition.
在一切事务上的
of the King's supremacy.
至高无上的地位 无论精神信仰或俗世
in all matters, spiritual and temporal.
若有违抗…
Those who refuse to take it…
将视为叛国罪
will be accounted guilty of treason.
投入监狱
and sent to prison.
做得不错 大臣阁下
That is all well done, Mr. Secretary.
甚合我意
I am pleased.
终究还是需要宣誓
So it must be sworn by oath, after all.
上帝保佑
God save us.
[拉丁语]我信唯一 至圣 至公
Et unam sanctam catholicam.
[拉丁语]由使徒传下的教会
et apostolicam ecclesian.
[拉丁语]以圣父 圣子
In nomine Patris et Fillii.
[拉丁语]圣灵的名义
et Spiritu Sancti.
阿门
Amen.
国王还是如此冥顽不灵吗
Does the King remain obdurate?
是的 圣父
Yes, Holy Father.
他拒绝听取建议
He refuses to listen to advice.
强迫所有信徒破坏他们的誓言
And he forces all true believers to perjure their immortal souls.
- 此话怎讲？- 他们必须
- How so? - They must all.
宣誓国王是英国教会之首
swear an oath that the King is head of the English church.
如有违抗即被关进监狱
Those who refuse are put in prison.
如同我们基督里的弟兄 费施尔主教
Like our brother in Christ, Bishop Fisher.
是的 圣父
Yes, Holy Father.
无法接受
This is unacceptable.
一旦狼进入羊栏
The shepherd cannot stand idly by.
威吓羊群之时
while the wolf enters the fold.
牧羊人是不会袖手旁观的
and threatens his flock.
我决定任命费施尔为红衣主教
I have decided to make Fisher a Cardinal.
你把他的冠冕送到英格兰
You will send his hat to England.
我们来看看国王是否胆敢
Let's see if the King is still prepared.
指控 折磨一位教会亲王
to prosecute and torture a Prince of the Church.
布赖恩夫人
Ah! Mistress Bryan.
- 早安 - 陛下
- A very good morning to you. - Your Majesty.
我在巡行
I'm on progress.
我来探望我的女儿 她怎么样
I've come to see my daughter. How is she?
她各方面都会令陛下感到无上光荣
She is a credit to Your Majesty in every way.
我的伊丽莎白
My Elizabeth.
说不定 布赖恩夫人 也许有一天
Who knows, Mistress Bryan, perhaps one day.
这个小姑娘会统治整个王国
this little girl will preside over empires.
原谅我
Please forgive me.
我没有太多时间
I don't have much time.
感谢尔等照料我们心爱的公主
Thank you for all your care toward our beloved Princess.
陛下
Your Majesty.
埃莉诺夫人
Lady Eleanor.
大人
My Lord.
你以为别人发现不了你的秘密？
How did you suppose no one would find out your secret?
- 今天 - 你的房间被搜查过了
- I… - Your chamber was searched today.
什么
My Lord…?
发现了一些珠宝 你没有将它们藏匿妥当
The jewels were found. You did not hide them well enough.
- 珠宝？我不… - 王后陛下的珠宝
- Jewels…? I don't… - Her Majesty's jewels.
你偷窃的珠宝
The ones you stole.
- 不可能 - 我说千真万确
- It's not true! - And I say it is true.
你的偷窃罪行一旦曝光
And if your crimes were ever reported,
你还指望谁能相信你
who do you suppose would believe you?
毕竟 埃莉诺夫人
After all, Lady Eleanor,
没人会凭白无故控告你
no one could accuse you of being innocent…
不是吗
could they?
要我怎么做？
What am I to do?
离开宫廷
Leave court.
回家
Go back to your family.
看看他们是否还欢迎你
See if they will have you.
玛琪表妹 谢尔顿夫人
Cousin Madge! Lady Sheldon,
- 你们在看什么？- 没什么 女士
- What are you reading? - Nothing, my Lady.
只是… 一些诗
Just some… poetry.
托马斯·怀特爵士写的
By Sir Thomas Wyatt.
拿过来
Give it here.
你们不应该在这种小事上
You should not be wasting your time.
浪费时间
on such trifles.
如果你们一定要在侍奉我的时候读
If you must read, when you are supposed to be attending on me,
就去读那本书
then you should read that book!
你们将学到更多
You will learn a great deal more from it,
也许会更聪明
perhaps even some wisdom.
是 女士
Yes, Madam.
现在去做正经事吧
Now go about your business.
王后陛下 威尔特郡伯爵驾到
The Earl of Wiltshire, Your Majesty.
爸爸
Papa.
陛下
Your Majesty.
你看起来不错
You look well.
我相信你已开始能看出来
And I believe you're already showing.
一点点 您去巴黎的旅行如何？
A little. How was your trip to Paris?
去那…
It was…
法国国王可不好对付
King Francis is not the easiest man to deal with.
他送来结婚礼物给你 但他装作
He sends you wedding presents, yet he pretends.
他不能正式承认你是王后
he cannot officially recognize you as Queen.
因为凯瑟琳还活着
As long as Katherine remains alive.
国王怎么样？
How is the King?
你的状态该会让他很满意
He must be pleased at your condition.
- 是的 - 不过… ？
- He is. - But…?
一切都很好
Everything is fine.
但在我上次怀孕的时候 国王有了个情妇
But when I was last with child, the King took a mistress.
如今…
And now…
如今我怕他会重蹈旧辙
now I fear he will take another,
因为我必须为了孩子而小心谨慎
since I must be careful for the sake of the child.
不能让他和我鱼水之欢
and not let him enjoy his conjugal rights.
对于男人而言这是正常的
It is natural for a man,
当他的妻子怀孕而不愿和他同床时
when his wife is big with child and not willing to lie with him,
自然会出去找点其它暂时的抚慰
to find some temporary consolation elsewhere.
而对于国王来说 更是合乎情理
And for Kings, it is properly expected.
亲爱的
Sweetheart,
听我说 你的和我们的危机
listen to me. The danger to you,
并非国王有了情妇
and to us, is not that the King takes a mistress…
而是他找错了情妇
but that he takes the wrong one.
不仅不服我们掌控
Someone we can't control,
还会寻求掌控国王的那种
or who would seek to control the King.
但如果假设
But if you suppose.
国王确实会有情妇
the King is sure to take a mistress,
那么一定要确保
then make sure.
情妇是你的选择
she is your choice,
而不是他的
and not his.
我得向国王汇报了 一会见
I must make my report to the King. I'll see you later.
- 大臣阁下 - 尊敬的费施尔主教
- Mr. Secretary. - Reverend Fisher.
我来就想看看他们有没有好好待你
I just came to see if you were being well treated.
这样说的话 我这衰老的胃
As to that, my aged stomach.
应负不了狱卒送来的腐臭的饭菜
cannot cope with the rank food the jailor brings.
但那没什么 因为那只是身体上的折磨 而无关灵魂
But that is nothing, since it pertains to my body and not my soul.
你还没接受宣誓
You have not taken the Oath.
- 没有 - 为什么不？
- No. - Why not?
你不认为国王的婚姻合理合法？
Do you refuse to accept that the King's marriage is proper and legal?
我相信陛下他这样想
I believe His Majesty thinks it so.
但你不？
But you don't?
不
No.
我只相信我一直坚信的…
I believe what I have always believed.
国王与凯瑟琳的婚姻仍然有效
that the King's marriage to Queen Katherine is still valid,
且不能被任何人破坏
and can be undone by no man,
即使是克莱默大主教也不行
not even Archbishop Cranmer.
那么你现在质疑
And do you dispute.
吾王现在是教会的最高领袖？
that the King is Supreme Head of the Church now?
是的 我毫不犹豫的质疑
Yes, I do. Most emphatically.
吾王只是国君 绝非世间
The King our Sovereign Lord is not the Supreme Head on earth.
英格兰教会的最高领袖
of the Church of England.
告诉我
Tell me:
托马斯·莫尔爵士怎么样了？
How is Sir Thomas More?
看守
Jailor!
我会…
I will…
看看饭菜的质量能不能提高
see if the quality of your food can be improved.
多谢了
Thank you.
你为什么要驱逐埃莉诺夫人？
Why did you get rid of Lady Eleanor?
她偷了我珍贵的东西
She stole something precious from me.
你确定是她偷的吗？
Are you sure she stole it?
是的 我有证据
Yes. I had the evidence.
我没的选择
I had no choice.
我希望陛下不至于
I hope Your Majesty is not.
太失望？
too disappointed?
无论如何
In any case,
我有些东西给你
I have something for you.
陛下
Your Majesty.
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth.
谢谢
Thank you.
这是何事？
What's this?
陛下 有一些小修道院
Majesty, there are a number of small monastic institutions.
我有理由相信 需要调查一下
I have had cause to investigate.
修道士们不愿意接受誓言
The monks there refuse to take the Oath.
比起您 他们更愿意效忠罗马教廷
They'd rather serve the Vicar of Rome than you.
这是关于遣散他们的议案
This is a Bill for their dissolution.
这笔可观的财产
The very considerable wealth of these houses.
随即将被转到您的国库
will thus be transferred to Your Majesty's exchequer.
接下来？
Well?
陛下 我刚刚听说教皇意欲
Majesty, I have just heard that the Pope intends.
任命费施尔神父为红衣主教
to make Reverend Fisher a Cardinal.
显然他已经派发了主教冠冕
Apparently he has already despatched a Cardinal's hat.
费施尔将把它戴在肩膀上
Then Fisher will have to wear it upon his shoulders!
因为当帽子到达时 费施尔将已经被处死
For by the time it gets here, he won't have a head to put it on!
莫尔是什么情况？
And what of More?
我想知道
I want to know!
他接受誓言吗？
Will he take the oath?
她怎么样？吃的怎么样？
How is she? Does she feed well?
陛下 他一切都好 几乎没怎么哭
She is good in every way, Your Majesty. And hardly cries at all.
就好像她已经知道她是公主了
as if she already knows that she is a Princess.
我爱你 伊丽莎白
I love you, Elizabeth.
我全身心的爱你
I love you with all my heart.
我希望你永不被忘记
and I bid you never forget it.
嘘… 嘘…
Shh… shh…
陛下
Your Majesty.
在我离开前 我想和玛莉女士说几句话
Before I leave, I wish to say something to the Lady Mary.
玛莉女士…
Lady Mary…
玛莉女士 我怀着善意而来
Lady Mary, I am here in kindness.
我想欢迎你回到宫廷
I would welcome you back to court,
并促使你和你父亲和解
and reconcile you with your father,
只要你接受我是王后
if you will only accept me as Queen.
除了母亲 我不认为任何人是王后
I recognize no Queen but my mother.
但如果国王的情妇
But if the King's mistress.
乐意代我向国王说情…
would intercede with the King on my behalf…
那么我会很感激
then I would be grateful.
- 托马斯·莫尔爵士来访 - 托马斯爵士
- Sir Thomas More. - Sir Thomas.
大臣阁下
Mr. Secretary.
请坐 这是非正式会面
Please be seated. This is but an informal occasion.
来杯酒吗？
A little ale, perhaps?
不 谢谢
No, thank you.
我相信你我都知道我们
I'm sure we both know the object.
现在在这里的原因
which has brought us together.
有很多关于你的谣言 托马斯爵士
It is very widely rumoured, Sir Thomas,
你将拒绝接受继承誓言
that you will refuse to take the Oath of Succession.
我很开诚布公的跟你说
I say this to you very openly and sincerely:
我不希望一个多年来侍奉吾王
That I wish no harm to come to a great man.
蒙受王恩的为人
who has for years enjoyed and deserved.
受到任何伤害
His Majesty's good graces.
我宁愿看到我儿子死 也不愿你受伤害
I would rather lose my own son than see any hurt come to you.
我能听听你对国王新婚的意见吗？
May I ask your opinion of the King's new marriage?
没意见
I have no opinion.
我既没有说闲话 也没有私下议论
I neither murmur at it, nor dispute upon it;
我不会 永远不会
I never did and never will.
那么对于吾王的「英格兰教会的
Then what of His Majesty's claim to Supremacy.
最高领袖「你有何见解？
over the Church in England?
本来我对此事仍不能确定…
I was unsure about this matter.
直到我重读了陛下写的手册：
until I re-read His Majesty's own pamphlet:
《为七项圣礼辩护》
The "Assertio septum Sacramentorum".
实际上
In fact,
我这里有个副本
I have a copy of it here.
当然 在这本手册里 吾王确定了
Of course, in the pamphlet, the King asserts.
教皇制度的神圣起源
the divine origin of the papacy.
教皇的权威
The Pope's supremacy descends directly.
从圣彼得磐石上直接传承下来
from the Rock of St. Peter.
我想你会发现陛下的一些论点
I think you'll find His Majesty's arguments are as…
无论是当时还是现在
persuasive and powerful now.
都很有说服力
as they were when he first wrote them.
你会宣誓吗？
Will you take the Oath?
我想我不用提醒你
I need hardly remind you.
如果不这么做会有什么后果
of the consequences of not doing so.
大臣阁下
Mr. Secretary,
我对国王无比衷心
I am the King's loyal subject.
不会出口对他不利
I say no harm,
不会图谋对他不利
I think no harm,
我也只希望每人都好
but I wish everybody good.
如果有此良好信念仍不足以使人存活
And if this be not enough to keep a man alive, in good faith,
- 我也不想残喘于世了 - 托马斯阁下
- I long not to live. - Sir Thomas…
你应该知道国王陛下完全不想强迫你
You should know that the King himself has no mind.
他只是希望你通情达理
to coerce you. He simply asks you to relent.
屈就于他的请求 答应去宣誓
and condescend to his request that you take the Oath.
克伦威尔先生 请代向国王转达我无比忠诚
Mr. Cromwell, please impart to the King my utter faithfulness,
真诚 和对他的忠心
truthfulness, and loyalty to him.
玛琪表妹
Cousin Madge.
是的 夫人
Yes, Madam?
来和我聊聊天
Come and talk to me.
我想你一定有很多仰慕者
I suppose you have many admirers?
是的
Yes,
但我一直记得王后陛下的教导
but I always remember what Your Majesty told us,
不能放荡 要有一个标准
about not being lewd and setting a standard.
我相信你一定是这么做的
I'm sure you do.
但你会不会很惊讶 如果得知你的仰慕者中
But would it surprise you to learn that one of your admirers.
包括国王陛下
is the King?
这不是真的
It's not true!
这是真的
It is true.
现在 你会不会更惊讶
Now, would it surprise you even more if I told you.
如果我说我会许可你做他的情人
that you would have my blessing to become his mistress?
夫人
Madam!
当我怀着孩子的时候 国王陛下
While I am with child, His Majesty needs to be able to lie.
需要有另一个女人陪着
with another woman.
他是很有激情的男人
He is a passionate man.
但是那个女人 必须是我能够信任的
But she must be someone I can trust.
她的家庭 也是我信任的
Whose family I can trust,
正如你
like yours.
毕竟
After all,
我们是一家人
we are family.
你也是改革运动的支持者
And you are reformers.
是的王后陛下 我已经乐意的宣誓了
Yes, Your Majesty. We all gladly took the oath.
那你乐意将国王带上你的床吗？
And now will you gladly take the King to your bed?
皇室使臣阁下觐见
His Excellency, the Imperial Ambassador.
- 阁下 - 国王陛下
- Excellency. - Your Majesty.
请您原谅 我特来请求您的怜悯
Forgive me, but I come here upon a mission of mercy.
- 怜悯？- 是的 您的女儿
- Mercy? - Very much so. Your daughter,
玛丽女士病了
the Lady Mary, has fallen ill,
她的医生也是这么认为的
even to the concern of her doctors.
我捎来了一封她母亲写的信
I have a letter written by her mother.
她想照顾她的孩子 她在信中说…
She would like to nurse her child. She writes…
我可以念吗？
If I may?
我带去的一点点安慰和欢乐
"A little comfort and mirth with me.
就可以使她痊愈一半
would be a half health to her."
我可以亲自照顾她
"I could care for her with my own hands.
亲自为她铺床
and put her in my own bed.
在她需要时照看着她
and watch with her when needful."
我会派我的私人医师给她做检查
I will send my personal physician to examine and help her.
但我不能允许玛丽和她妈妈在一起
But I cannot allow Mary and her mother to be together.
但是 国王陛下
But, Your Majesty,
这只是一个普通的母亲对她亲生女儿的心意
It is just the cry of any mother for any daughter.
这就是问题所在 她们不是普通的母女
But that's just it! They are not just any mother or daughter.
你肯定她们不会联合起来密谋反抗我吗
Do you not suppose they would conspire to plot against me?
我不这么认为
I cannot believe it.
你当然这么认为了 你知道会这样
Of course you can believe it! You know it happens.
有时候生病被用于政治目的
And that sometimes illness is used for political purpose.
你不认为
Do you not believe that.
凯瑟琳想让她的女儿成为居于人上的女王吗
Katherine wants Mary to be Queen above all else?
乔普斯先生
Mr. Chapuys,
凯瑟琳夫人是一个骄傲顽固的人
Lady Katherine is a very proud stubborn woman.
她也拥有十足的勇气
of very great and high courage.
她可以召集一个军队 占领一方土地
She could muster an army, take the field.
然后对我发动战争
and wage a war against me.
就像她的母亲伊莎贝拉在西班牙曾发动的战争
as fierce as any her mother Isabella ever waged in Spain.
难道不是吗？
Is that not true?
我已经被召唤
I've been handed a summons…
至朗伯斯宫（坎特伯雷大主教官邸）
to appear at Lambeth Palace…
去参加宣誓
to take the oath.
我想之后我会被监禁
I imagine I shall be imprisoned afterwards.
不 父亲
No! Father!
你们要互相照顾对方
You must be good to each other.
也要对其他人好
and to everyone else.
如果不能做到
Or, if you cannot be good,
至少尽量不做坏事
be the least bad you can be.
不 亲爱的
No, darling, no.
谢尔顿女士
Lady Sheldon.
- 王后呢？- 国王陛下
- Where's the Queen? - Your Majesty,
王后觉得有些不舒服
the Queen is feeling indisposed.
希望您能原谅她今早不骑马了
and asks you to forgive her not riding this morning.
- 当然 - 她说…
- Of course. - She…
她不知道国王陛下愿不愿意
She wondered if Your Majesty would be pleased if…
让我代替她 我是说 骑马
if I took her place. Riding, I mean.
如果王后同意了 为什么不呢？
If the Queen gives her permission, then why not?
谢尔顿女士
Lady Sheldon.
朗伯斯宫 伦敦
Lambeth Palace, London.
- 你叫什么名字 谢尔顿女士 - 玛格丽特 陛下
- What's your name, Lady Sheldon? - Margaret, Your Majesty.
尽管大家都叫我玛琪
Though people call me Madge.
那我叫你玛琪 可以吗？
Then I shall call you Madge-if you'll allow me?
当然 陛下
Of course, Your Majesty.
托马斯爵士
Sir Thomas.
你准备好要宣誓了吗
Are you now ready to swear the oath?
我能看看吗
May I see it?
谢谢
Thank you.
怎么样？
Well?
我不是想指责这份誓言或者它的撰写者
I don't mean to put at fault this oath or its makers.
更没有说对它宣誓的人有什么过错
or any man who swears to it.
我永远都不会谴责任何人的道德标准
And I will never condemn the conscience of any other man.
只是对我本人而言
But for myself, in good faith,
受良心驱使 我仅对继承人的合法性
my own conscience so moves me that I will swear to the validity.
表示认同 而不是其他部分
of the succession-yet not the rest of it,
以免我的灵魂
without jeopardizing my soul.
遭受永久的诅咒
to perpetual damnation.
我们很遗憾听到你这么说
We are very sorry to hear you say this.
你是第一个提出拒绝的人
You are almost the first to refuse it.
你的拒绝会使国王陛下
and your refusal will cause the King's highness.
对你产生愤怒
to be both indignant.
和怀疑
and suspicious of you.
这些是国会下院已宣誓的
Here are all the members of the Commons and the Lords.
所有成员和大人
who have sworn to take the oath.
- 还有神职人员 - 我不能宣誓
- The clergy too. - I myself cannot swear.
但我不会责怪任何宣誓的人
But I do not blame any other man who has sworn.
托马斯阁下 我们已经断定
Sir Thomas, we have come to the conclusion.
你完全不是一个
that, far from being.
对国王陛下真诚 忠心耿耿的人
a true and loyal servant to His Majesty,
而是一个前所未有的邪恶 叛逆
there never was a servant so villainous, so traitorous.
对自己的殿下如此不忠之徒
to his prince as you.
如果你拒绝宣誓
If you refuse to take the oath,
你不但会入狱
not only will you be imprisoned,
更有你想象不到的酷刑在等着你
but the most horrid things imaginable will be done to you.
大人 这些吓唬孩子可以 对我没用
My Lords, these threats are for children, not for me.
你是否承认
Do you deny.
你曾威胁诱导国王
that you bullied and persuaded the King,
违背他自己的意愿
against his conscience,
- 写下这本反对路德的册子 - 我当然否认
- to write this pamphlet against Luther? - Of course I deny it.
首先我决不会强迫任何人
In the first place I would never ask anyone,
无论他身份高贵或贫贱
be he ever so high or so low,
去做他们不愿做的事 第二
to act against his conscience. And secondly,
我记得反而是国王告诫我
I remember it was His Majesty who rather persuaded me.
教皇职位的重要性
of the paramount importance of the papacy.
我再问你最后一次
I ask you a final time,
在你被处以
before the awful penalties.
可怕的刑罚之前
are exacted upon you:
你为什么不宣誓？
Why will you not swear?
玛琪
Oh, Madge!
- 怎么了？- 玛琪
- What? - Madge!
我不知道 只是很有意思
I don't know. It's funny.
玛琪
Madge.
我喜欢你笑起来时候的酒窝 玛琪
I like your dimples when you laugh, Madge.
玛琪
Madge.
陛下
Your Majesty.
过来
Come here.
让我…
Let me…
离近一点
examine your dimples.
仔细端详你的酒窝
a little more closely.
托马斯爵士
Sir Thomas.
谢谢
Thank you.
对了 殿下也许会乐于知道
Oh… Your Highness might like to know that the Reverend Fisher.
费施尔神父就被关在你的下面
is lodged in the room down below.
祝你有好心情 大人
Good day to you, sir.